So error handling is important to consider when creating a robust application.
And here we'll cover error handling using the ESP ADF.
And we'll start with an overview of error handling and then we'll talk about error codes, converting
error codes to error messages using the ESP Error Check macro and error handling patterns or strategies
that you may want to consider in your development.
So to get started, let's take a look at the impressive documentation.
So the errors we're discussing here are runtime errors.
And again, handling these errors is an important aspect of developing robust applications.
And we can have a couple of different types of errors.
The first type mentioned here are categorized as recoverable errors, which are errors indicated by
functions through return values or error codes.
Unrecoverable or fatal errors can result from failed assertions, for example, using the assert macro
and equivalent methods.
And if we follow the assertions link, you may be familiar with the assert function defined in assert
dot h, but when asserting a value of the type esp error type is equal to ESP OC.
The ESP error check macro is used instead of assert.
And so CPU exceptions are considered fatal, which could be access to protected regions of memory,
illegal instructions, etc..
Then you also have system level checks like watchdog timeout cache access, error, stack overflow,
stack smashing heap corruption, etc. And this guide explains ESP IDF error handling mechanisms related
to recoverable errors and provide some common error handling patterns.
And I'll show you some patterns used in the course source code as well.
And you could always check out this link for instructions on diagnosing unrecoverable errors.
And you may want to mark this as a favorite in your ESP 32 resources as you're eventually bound to run
into the panic handler which handles these fatal errors.
So let's move on to our codes.
Most ESP specific functions use ESP error type to return error codes.
And ESP type is assigned integer type, which you can find in the esp h file from the ESP and success
or no error is indicated with the ESP code, which is defined as zero.
And common error codes for generic failures like out of memory, invalid argument and timeout etc. are
defined here as well.
And you also have other error codes defined in various ESP EDF header files.
Also using preprocessor defines starting with the ESP prefix.
For example, there are NVS related error codes defined in the nonvolatile storage file, and here the
ESP error NVS base is defined as the starting number for the error codes and then each subsequent error
code is defined as an offset from the base.
And converting codes to error messages can also be useful when debugging by displaying the error messages
as strings on the terminal monitor.
This is possible for each error code defined in ESP ADF components, and the ESP error type can be converted
to an error code name using the ESP error to name or ESP error to name underscore our functions.
For example, we'll use ESP error to name for our non-volatile storage functions and in this example
we call NVS Open, which returns its status to ESP error.
And if it didn't return successful or ESP OC, we can then use ESP error to name and display its result
using print def or esp log.
So if you want to find out the exact reason that a function fails, try using these functions.
And the way it works is, is it finds the error code in a pre generated lookup table and returns it
string representation.
And here you have the lookup table defined here.
Where each entry in the table is an error code in message pair and ESP error to name underscore r can
be used when you need to also consider system error codes.
So here, if the error code is not found, then str error underscore r is used.
So back to the ESP air check macro, the ESP error check macro checks, the ESP error type value rather
than a bull condition.
And if the argument of ESP error check is not equal to ESP, then the error message is printed on the
console and the abort function is called and on the console.
Your error message will look like this.
So here in the documentation it says that if the ADF monitor is used, addresses in the backtrace will
be converted to file names and line numbers.
And the first line mentions the error code as a hexadecimal value and the identifier used for this error
in the source code and the subsequent lines show the location in the program where ESP Error Check Macro
was called and the expression which was passed to the macro as an argument.
Then the backtrace is printed, which is part of the panic handler output common to all fatal errors.
And if you don't want to abort but still have the convenience of this macro, you can always use the
ESP error check without abort macro.
Now let's review some strategies for handling these errors.
So the documentation recommends the following strategies.
You can first attempt to recover.
And depending on the situation, we may want to try the following methods.
You can retry the call like in the below where the function call is re attempted while the result is
timed out.
Or you can attempt to d initialize the driver and re initialize it again and or fix the error condition
using an out of band mechanism.
For example, reset an external peripheral which is not responding and for an example of where we attempt
to recover from errors.
I'd like to show you the inverse initialization that we use in main.
So here, if the NBS flash init function returns with either of the following errors, then we erase
the flash and re initialize it.
So this is one example of attempting to recover and another possible response would be to propagate
the error to the caller.
And here's an example of that.
And finally, you can designate certain functions as unrecoverable errors by using ESP check.
So you'll need to decide for yourself when using ESP or check makes sense in your application.
As mentioned here, many ESP ADF examples and I often do this myself use ESP error checks to handle
errors from various APIs and this is not the best practice for applications and is done to make example
code more concise so it may be convenient to use.
However, you'll need to put more thought into error handling and apply the appropriate error handling
patterns when you need your firmware to be production ready.
All right.
So that's it for now.
And see you in the next lesson.